Guide to the Walter McGowan Upchurch Papers, 1841-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Walter McGowan Upchurch papers 1841-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Upchurch, Walter McGowan.
8.0 Linear Feet Approximately 4600 Items
Member of Board of Trustees at Duke University; senior vice-president of Shell Companies Foundation, Inc.
Collection spans the years 1841-1977, with the bulk dating from 1930-1977, and contains personal correspondence among members of the Upchurch family, including correspondence between Upchurch and his brother during World War II, when they were both serving in the U.S. Navy; professional correspondence concerning Duke University administrative affairs; genealogical materials for the Upchurch, Daniel, and Meadows families of North Carolina; commemorative material on Upchurch's mother, Minnie Gertrude (Daniel) Upchurch; and photographs, clippings, programs, and school materials. Much of the personal materials reveals the life of a middle-class North Carolina family during the first half of the 20th century. One personal letter is from John Steinbeck's sister, Beth Ainsworthy, and contains comments on Steinbeck and relationships in the Steinbeck family. Another group of materials relates to the world premiere of Samuel Barber's opera, ANTONY AND CLEOPATRA, at the Lincoln Center in N.Y. on Sept. 16, 1966. Included are invitations, commemorative programs and booklets, and the opera libretto. Other materials include Shell Development Company records on personnel issues such as labor relations and salary administration; and Shell Companies Foundation records (1963-1974), chiefly relating to the foundation's endowments, scholarships, and grants, as well as the company's donation budgets from 1969-1974.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Walter McGowan Upchurch Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1972-1979.
Collection Overview
The Walter McGowan Upchurch Papers span the years 1841-1977, with the bulk dating from 1930-1977. The collection contains personal correspondence among members of the Upchurch family, including correspondence between Upchurch and his brother during WWII, when they were both serving in the U.S. Navy; professional correspondence concerning Duke University administrative affairs; genealogical materials for the Upchurch, Daniel, and Meadows families of North Carolina; commemorative material on Upchurch's mother, Minnie Gertrude (Daniel) Upchurch; and photographs, clippings, programs, and school materials. Much of the personal materials reveals the life of a middle-class North Carolina family during the first half of the 20th century. One personal letter is from John Steinbeck's sister, Beth Ainsworthy, and contains comments on Steinbeck and relationships in the Steinbeck family. Another group of materials relates to the world premiere of Samuel Barber's opera, ANTONY AND CLEOPATRA, at the Lincoln Center in N.Y. on Sept. 16, 1966. Included are invitations, commemorative programs and booklets, and the opera libretto. Other materials include Shell Development Company records on personnel issues such as labor relations and salary administration, coming from the Emeryville Laboratories, seen as one of the most progressive work environments in the United States; and Shell Companies Foundation records (1963-1974), chiefly relating to the foundation's endowments, scholarships, and grants, as well as the company's donation budgets from 1969-1974.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Upchurch family
Daniels family
Meadows family
Upchurch, Minnie Gertrude
Steinbeck, John, 1902-1968
Ainsworth, Beth
Steinbeck family
Barber, Samuel, 1910-1981. Antony and Cleopatra
United States. Navy -- Military life
Duke University -- History
Duke University. Board of Trustees
Labor unions -- California
Petroleum industry and trade -- California
Shell Development Company
Universities and colleges -- North Carolina
Endowments -- United States
World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives
Personnel management -- United States
North Carolina -- Social life and customs
Related Material
W. M. Upchurch Records, 1927-1988
University Archives, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1909-1977, (8 boxes)
  - General, 1926-1939 (Box 1)
  - General, 1940-1971 (Box 2)
  - Mr. Upchurch and Fannie Yarborough Mitchell, 1942-1952 (Box 3)
  - Family, 1909-1945, June (Box 4)
  - Family, 1945, July-1948, July (Box 5)
  - Family, 1948, Aug.-1953 (Box 6)
  - Family, 1954-1959 (Box 7)
  - Family, 1960-1971 (Box 8)
  - General, 1970-1977
- Duke University Series, 1931-1971, (1.5 boxes)
  - Duke University files (Box 9)
    - Programs of Summer School service of worship in Duke University Chapel, 1938-1941
    - Duke Memorial Church Choir records, 1931-1941; 1971
    - Duke University Summer School Choir records, 1938-1941
  - Clippings and pictures
  - Duke University files (Box 14)
- Naval Files Series, 1917-1952, (2.5 boxes)
  - Navy Department Operating Petroleum Facilities records, 1917-1946 (Box 10)
    - Navy Department Operating Petroleum Facilities records: Labor Relations Reporter. Vol. 16, No.26 (Aug. 27, 1945) (Box 11)
    - U.S. Naval Reserve officer files, 1945-1952 (Box 14)
- Shell Development Company Records Series, 1942-1974, (4 boxes)
  Focusing on Shell Development Laboratories at Emeryville, California. Known as progressive work envirnoment, includes salary studies, personnel evaluation templates; union relations, and development notes from 1928-1970. Decommissioned in 1972. Does not seem to contain individually identifiable personnel records.
  - Shell Development Company Records, 1942-1950 (Box 12)
  - Shell Development Company Records, 1944-1950 (Box 13)
  - Shell Development Company Personnel Records, 1947-1970 (Box 17)
  - Shell Companies Foundation Records, 1963-1974 (Box 18)
    - Shell Grants, 1969 (pamphlets)
    - The Royal Dutch/Shell Group of Companies, 1968
- Personal Memorabilia Series, 1910-1974, (2 boxes)
  Mementoes and other materials from Walter Upchurch's life and career.
  - Certificates and diplomas; clippings; photographs (1910-1950s); and volumes (includes baby album) (Box 15)
  - Printed material, 1924-1974 (Box 16)
    Small pamphlets covering Walter Upchurch's participation or attendance in high school and Duke Unviersity events as well as local gatherings. Also contains 2 silk scrolls commemorating the opening of the Met Opera House, New York City, 1966.